# Lukas José Ferrer

https://github.com/Ljferrer lukasjferrer@gmail.com || 310.801.8751

## **ABOUT MF**

I studied Bio, EE, and AI to see neurons from all three perspectives. My initial work on electrophysiology, medical devices, and VR gave me experience bringing research into reality. As a self taught programmer, I now focus on Deep Learning and NLP applied towards Information Retrieval Systems.

## **EDUCATION**

## M.S. BIOMEDICAL ENG.

USC | VITERBI

August 2017 | Los Angeles, CA Focus: Electrophysiology, Medical Device Regulations, & Agile Software Development

## **B.S. BIOMEDICAL ENG.**

USC | Viterbi

May 2016 | Los Angeles, CA Focus: Medical Devices & Physiological Modeling

# TOOLS

## **PYTHON**

PyTorch | FastAI TensorFlow | Keras TensorBoard Numpy SpaCy Faiss REST | Requests

#### **SOFTWARE**

Linux | Ubuntu | CentOS Amazon Web Services Docker MATLAB LabVIEW SolidWorks

# LINKS

LinkedIn || **lukas-ferrer** GitHub || **Ljferrer** 

## **EXPERIENCE**

# **INFORMATION SCIENCES INSTITUTE** | RESEARCH PROGRAMMER

May 2018 - Present | Marina del Rey, CA

- SARAL Using Deep Learning for low resource, Neural Machine Translation
- Reimplemented several academic papers focusing on Transformers
- Improved our existing NMT system's performance to be competitive with or better than Google Translate across several language pairs
- Operationalized our models to fit into the larger SARAL pipeline i.e. Audio/Text Database -> ASR -> NMT -> IR -> Summarization -> User
- **SAGE** Implemented the backend of SAGE's **Research Tool**, an information retrieval tool for our news database
- Set up a host server on AWS and automated an ingestion pipeline that continuously updates the Research Tool with +100,000 news articles per day from LexisNexis
- Demonstrated a meaningful improvement in search quality over previously implemented system

### KECK RADIOMICS LAB | Volunteer Researcher

Oct 2016 - Nov 2017 | Los Angeles, CA

- Analyzed spectral and texture features of CT images with a particular focus on boundary conditions for tissue segmentation in a HIPAA compliant setting
- Characterized the statistical variance of images across different CT machines
- Reported results and findings in weekly lab meetings with an interdisciplinary team

## RECALL VR | CREATOR AND TEAM LEAD

Aug 2015 - May 2016 | USC GamePipe Lab

- Envisioned and pursued the creation of an experimental, Virtual Reality learning accelerator designed to leverage a student's natural spatial awareness to increase memory retention (sometimes called The Memory Palace Technique)
- Led 16+ students with skill sets ranging from architecture and animation to computer science and business under an Agile development framework
- Won 1st place at the 2016 Viterbi Senior Design Expo

## **HEMODIALYSIS CATHETER** | FINAL PROJECT

May 2015 - Aug 2015 | USC MPTX 513

- Worked in a team of four to create a complete 510(k), simulating the process of obtaining FDA clearance to market
- Designed a Class II, implantable hemodialysis catheter that was substantially equivalent to two predicate devices in terms of fabrication, materials, and labeled use, while novel with its blood flow separating tip
- Modeled the implanted device in SolidWorks to render blood flow simulations
- Familiar with the continuous product life cycle of medical devices in compliance with ISO and CFR guidelines

#### **SYNTOUCH** | ROBOTICS INTERN

Feb 2014 - Nov 2014 | Los Angeles, CA

- Fabricated a robotic test fixture to explore alternative applications of SynTouch's new tactile sensor, the NumaTac
- Documented the design process from the Bill of Materials to assembly
- Reported weekly progress at the Medical Device Development & Fabrication Lab at USC under the direction of Dr. Gerald E. Loeb